Let's start to formalize the problem of learning a good word embedding.
When you implement an algorithm to
learn a word embedding, what you end up learning is an
embedding matrix. Let's take a look at what that means.
Let's say, as usual we're using
our 10,000-word vocabulary. So, the vocabulary has A,
Aaron, Orange, Zulu, maybe also unknown word as a token.
What we're going to do is
learn embedding matrix E, which is going
to be a 300 dimensional by 10,000 dimensional matrix, if you have 10,000 words vocabulary
or maybe 10,001 is unknown word token,there's one extra token.
And the columns of this matrix would be the
different embeddings for the
10,000 different words you have in your vocabulary. So, Orange was word number
6257 in our vocabulary of 10,000 words. So, one piece of notation
we'll use is that 06257 was the one-hot vector with
zeros everywhere and a one in position 6257. And so, this will be a
10,000-dimensional vector with a one in just one position.
So, this isn't quite a drawn scale. Yes, this should be as tall
as the embedding matrix on the left is wide.
And if the embedding matrix is called capital E then notice that if you take E
and multiply it by just one-hot vector by 0 of 6257,
then this will be a 300-dimensional vector.
So, E is 300 by 10,000 and 0 is 10,000 by 1.
So, the product will be 300 by 1,
so with 300-dimensional vector and notice that
to compute the first element of this vector,
of this 300-dimensional vector,
what you do is you will multiply the first row of the matrix E with this.
But all of these elements are zero except for
element 6257 and so you end up with zero times this,
zero times this, zero times this, and so on.
And then, 1 times whatever this is,
and zero times this, zero times this, zero times and so on.
And so, you end up with the first element as whatever is that elements up there,
under the Orange column.
And then, for the second element of this 300-dimensional vector we're computing,
you would take the vector
0657 and multiply it by the second row with the matrix E. So again,
you have zero times this,
plus zero times this,
plus zero times all of these are the elements and then one times this,
and then zero times everything else and add that together.
So you end up with this and so on as you go down the rest of this column.
So, that's why the embedding matrix E times this one-hot vector here winds up
selecting out this 300-dimensional column corresponding to the word Orange.
So, this is going to be equal to E 6257 which
is the notation we're going to use to represent
the embedding vector that 300 by one dimensional vector for the word Orange.